<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-10-09T14:22:21-04:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sylvan Zheng</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Return to Red Rocks</title><link href="/2024/05/08/return-to-red-rocks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Return to Red Rocks" /><published>2024-05-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-05-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2024/05/08/return-to-red-rocks</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/05/08/return-to-red-rocks.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="rainbow-wall-original-route">Rainbow Wall (Original Route)</h1>

<p>Red Rocks is probably the most popular multi pitch trad area in the US.
It’s not the <em>best</em> one (obviously, that honor goes to Yosemite Valley),
but the proximity to the urban conveniences of Las Vegas,
the generous bolting, the positive gym-like flakes of patina, and stable weather
all contribute to the most accessible long multipitch destination in the country.
Not that I’m complaining about the crowds (well, maybe a little bit).</p>

<p>One of the coolest things about Red Rocks is that it offers a nice “ladder” of progressively
harder and bigger routes starting way at the easiest end of the grade scale.
Climbers return year after year, cutting their teeth on continuously gnarlier objectives.
Climb Chrimson Chrysalis (5.8) one year, come back the next for Epinephrine (5.9).
Dream about climbing Inti Watana (5.10); tick that one off and start looking at the topo for Levitation 29 (5.11).</p>

<p>Looming over it all (literally) is the Original Route on Rainbow Wall (5.12), visible from almost any point in the Scenic Loop drive.
There are more difficult multipitch routes in the canyons that seem very good (Jet Stream 5.13a, in particular),
but the Original Route on Rainbow Wall is arguably the second most hard classic multipitch sandstone route in the country
(the first place honor goes of course, to Moonlight Buttress in Zion National Park). 
The OR also has the somewhat niche honor of being perhaps the easiest route that Alex Honnold gained some notoriety from free soloing
back in the day.
Doing all of “famous Honnold solos” with a rope wouldn’t be a bad lifetime goal for a mere mortal trad climber:
Original Route on Rainbow Wall, Moonlight Buttress, Sendero Luminoso, Astroman and Rostrum (in a day), University Wall, Freerider.</p>

<p><img src="/images/rbw/overview.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>I originally planned a trip to try Rainbow wall in spring of 2023, but I broke my ankle that winter,
forcing me to cancel my plans. 15 months later, my ankle was (mostly) in serviceable shape and the opportunity
presented itself to try the route in May.</p>

<p>I was nervous going in; I hadn’t climbed multipitch trad since the previous summer.
Last time Ceri and I climbed together we nearly onsighted Freeway (5.11c) in Squamish. 
I was absolutely thrashed at the top of the wall, struggling to maintain control 
on mellow 5.10 terrain. The idea of climbing a longer, harder route guarded by a steep approach
after a period of basically no trad climbing practice and certainly zero cardio training
seemed laughable. Freeway starts off hard and gradually tapers off; meanwhile Rainbow Walls’
two 5.12a crux pitches come back to back near the top of the climb. But rumors of the route whispered
‘‘the cruxes are brief and well protected… face climbing strength is more important
than crack climbing strength… anyone clipping bolts at the Gallery should go clip bolts on Rainbow Wall instead.’’ 
So I texted Ceri, bought a plane ticket, and started doing rope laps at the gym once a week.</p>

<p>The week before the trip I had done maybe one or two cardio workouts
and still couldn’t fathom the idea of climbing 5.12 after a handful of 5.11 pitches in the gym.
But I managed to flash Brave New World (5.12a) and Gravity’s Rainbow (5.12c) at the Gunks in a day;
my trad leading head and fitness were starting to come back.</p>

<p>Our first objective upon landing in Vegas was Nightcrawler (5.10+), which conveniently lies just across 
the canyon from Rainbow Wall. Our idea was to familiarize ourselves with the approach, which at a bit over 
2 miles and 2000’ of elevation gain we wanted to do as quickly and efficiently on the morning of our Rainbow Wall attempt 
as possible. Some parties hike in camping gear and bivy at the base of the route. This strategy was 
out of the question, since our plan was to do the route in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2cis-fnK5Zo">a push</a>. 
We made several wrong turns on our way into Juniper canyon, 
but took our time and eventually found a reliable and easy trail. Nightcrawler went smoothly, with Ceri linking 
the first two pitches into a mega rope stretcher before I linked the next two to the top. 
Despite sending fairly easily, the sandstone felt a bit unfamiliar; we both felt a bit shaky on the rock.
The idea of having to climb over twice as many similarly graded pitches on Rainbow Wall before busting out
some 5.12 remained intimidating.</p>

<p>After rappelling Nightcrawler we made the game-time decision to jaunt over to the base of Rainbow Wall and 
stash our climbing gear at the base. This removes some purity from our planned in-a-day ascent, but given that
we were already deep in Juniper Canyon it almost seemed more contrived not to. The approach slabs proved
incredibly punishing on the quads, although the “death slab” portion proved to be a lot more mellow than we 
anticipated. We deposited our planned rack, rope, harnesses, helmets, climbing shoes discreetly
under a boulder and hobbled out of the canyon.</p>

<p><img src="/images/rbw/approach.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>36 hours later, we were on our way. We left the Pine Creek parking lot at 6:25AM only with daypacks filled with water and food,
posing as simple hikers to the handful of parties eagerly racking up by their cars.
Thanks to our rehearsal and our light packs the approach went smoothly, making it to the base of the wall in about 1:40.
A couple other parties showed up shortly after we arrived, and we began the multipitch ritual of
trying to size each other up to see if anyone would be a liability on the wall.</p>

<p>Ceri’s block was up first; the plan was for her to lead all the way to the end of the main corner system, 
dispatching several pitches between 5.10 and 5.11, while I would take the crux pitches in the second 
half of the route. Shade had crept onto the first pitch and the party behind us began to anxiously
arrange their gear, waiting for us to start. There were no more excuses; it was go time.</p>

<p>The climbing of the first few pitches proved to be mostly beautiful face climbing on my favorite Red Rock rock - solid chocolatey varnish,
and big open handed holds. The cruxes proved to be mostly brief and well protected, and we quickly started to put
some distance between us and the parties below. After breezing through the initial 6 pitch corner system Ceri simuled confidently through the scrambly section before it was my turn to lead. Some filler climbing deposited us at the base of the crux pitches of the route:
two back to back 5.12 corner pitches in the “red dihedral.” I was afraid of sustained slippery finger crack laybacking
and was pleasantly surprised to find (again) well protected, short crux sections with plenty of time to
feel all the crux holds before committing to just one or two hard moves before gaining easier terrain.</p>

<p>7 hours later, we were on top of the route. I had onsighted or flashed every pitch, and Ceri took only a couple of falls. 
On our way down, we discussed whether the route was soft, or whether
we had truly grown as climbers. The answer is probably a bit of both; the route, true to the rumors, 
features just so many bolts and a lot of face climbing. The longest stretch between comfortable stances is 
probably the 25 foot steep section on the second Red Dihedral pitch - most of the climbing on the route is really in the 5.10 or easier range. 
The difficult pitches are not necessarily mis-graded; the pulls are hard, but the moves are intuitive and use fairly 
ergonomic body positions.</p>

<p><img src="/images/rbw/crux.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p>Regardless, we were stoked to pull off a fast and fairly clean ascent of one of the hardest and most classic
multipitch routes in the country.</p>

<h2 id="approach-beta">Approach Beta</h2>

<p>Stay on the Pine Creek trail for longer than you think,
until you get to the Knoll Trail sign turnoff. Follow this trail that cuts across the hill to Juniper Canyon,
eventually depositing you in the wash significantly higher than if you try to approach Juniper canyon directly.
Boulder hop for about 10 minutes, passing the attractive problem Stand and Deliver V11, before cutting up 
left to the other side of the wash and gaining another easy trail that eventually takes you to the approach slabs of Rainbow Wall.
The death slabs are fairly mellow if you traverse quite far left and then back right. Follow the path of least resistance to
the base of the route.</p>

<h2 id="pitch-by-pitch">Pitch By Pitch</h2>

<p>P1 var. 5.11a. Rated 5.11c in the guidebook, 5.11a felt more appropriate. Follow the ramp/crack feature diagonally right to the main corner system. This pitch is mostly face climbing. The 12b original first pitch looks very high quality as well with only 1 hard move.
The belay here is hanging - linking 1/2 would be pretty mega.</p>

<p>P2 5.11c/d. (Guidebook 5.11d). One of my favorite pitches of the route. Combine face climbing and laybacking through
awesome open handed grips and beautiful varnish through a wandering line to the anchor. Belay stance is just OK here.</p>

<p>P3 5.10c (Guidebook 5.11a) Go up the corner. A good pitch, but kinda unmemorable. There’s a really good belay stance 
15’ before the anchor - a few hand size cams makes the belay much more comfortable.</p>

<p>P4 5.10d (Guidebook 5.11a) Climb past the freaky pillar and through the roof. This roof is way easier than the roof on Monkeyfinger in Zion. 
Rock quality begins to deteriorate here. It’s not choss, but just not as amazing as the lower pitches. OK belay.</p>

<p>P5 5.10b Climb up the corner, past an optional belay, to the top of the main corner system.</p>

<p>P6 4th/low 5th simul for 350’ up and right to an exposed step around a corner and up a face to Over the Rainbow Ledge.</p>

<p>P7 5.7 Short traverse to the left over junky rock and loose blocks to an anchor. I downclimbed a fair bit at some points.
We belayed at the lower station to eliminate rope drag.</p>

<p>P8 (Red Dihedral P1) 5.12a Launch up easy terrain to the base of the Red Dihedral. Bust out literally 1 hard move to 
gain a stance below the more famous boulder problem on the pitch and imagine free soloing it like Honnold. Choose
your own adventure to gain the jug and enjoy really fun 5.11- stemming and crack climbing on amazing rock.</p>

<p>P9 (RD P2) 5.12a The hardest pitch on the route, probably. Sustained layback and stemming with good holds that 
are sometimes a bit too far apart. You actually have to place gear in strenuous positions on this pitch! 
But the difficulties end fairly shortly. Climb more 5.11- to a weird stance to the left</p>

<p>P10 5.11a. Consider going back right and doing the 5.12b variation in the corner. Direct line, but worse rock quality.
The 5.11a pitch is probably 5.10- if you downclimb a bit and climb the right ramp. However, there’s a fun little
balance move if go direct off the belay, balancing on one good foot and cartwheel grab the ramp.</p>

<p>P11 5.10. Climb standard Red Rock patina to the summit.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="climbing" /><category term="trip report" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Original Route on Rainbow Wall]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Selective exposure, equilibrium effects, feedback loops</title><link href="/2023/09/11/more-equilibrium-effects.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selective exposure, equilibrium effects, feedback loops" /><published>2023-09-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-09-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/2023/09/11/more-equilibrium-effects</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/09/11/more-equilibrium-effects.html"><![CDATA[<p>Wow! Andrew Guess and coauthors have published in <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.abp9364">Science</a> a paper very similar to the one I described six months ago, collaborating with Facebook researchers to turn off ranked news feed in favor of chronological for radom users. As we might have anticipated, results are basically null, except that people clearly like chronological feed less and use Facebook/IG less often when it is turned on.</p>

<p>The idea that algorithm driven echo chambers causes polarization is just so painfully slippery. It sounds so plausible, but the issue is that basically no study has found evidence of this. Guess’s paper is basically state of the art when it comes to evaluating this question: turn off the algorithm, observe that like-minded exposure goes down and out-partisan content goes up, observe that polarization is unchanged. The conclusion that algorithm driven selective exposure doesn’t have an effect on polarization is hard to escape.</p>

<p>So the matter is finally settled? It’s hard to say. The idea seems like it will never die.</p>

<p>In my own research agenda, I’m working on understanding the same-but-opposite treatment; drastically increasing cross-cutting information (rather than scaling back like-minded, and hoping that some cross-cutting information takes its place). Much of the existing work on cross-cutting, or out-partisan news in social media is very good, but a lot of it tends to be rather conservative in treatment strength.</p>

<p>Looking forward, ranking algorithms may hve (tiny) direct effects, but what I’m really interested in are the equilibrium and feedback effects. How does the ranking algorithm (or more broadly, the way in which information is curated, distributed and consumed) change the way media companies, politicians, and influencers create content, and what are the political implications?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="causality" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Wow! Andrew Guess and coauthors have published in Science a paper very similar to the one I described six months ago, collaborating with Facebook researchers to turn off ranked news feed in favor of chronological for radom users. As we might have anticipated, results are basically null, except that people clearly like chronological feed less and use Facebook/IG less often when it is turned on.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">More on experimental equilibrium effects: a story from a particular social media company</title><link href="/2023/03/03/experiments-equilibrium-14.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="More on experimental equilibrium effects: a story from a particular social media company" /><published>2023-03-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-03-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2023/03/03/experiments-equilibrium-14</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/03/03/experiments-equilibrium-14.html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in the day when I used to work at a particular social media company I saw an internal report describing how ranking, or the process of changing the order of content in user feeds, was provably a good thing. This was in the face of both <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/how-to-use-facebook-no-algorithm/">public pressure</a> from scholars and commentators describing how content ranking algorithms created bias and opportunities for controversial, divisive content to go viral and other kinds of bad things.</p>

<p>The authors of the report had run a randomized experiment turning off ranking for a small portion of users for a few weeks. They showed that these users spent less time using the social media platform, scrolled past more stories, engaged less with meaningful content, and a whole host of other “negative” effects. Putting aside the obvious conflict of interest of some of these measurements (as in, maybe less time spent is actually a good thing, societally speaking), this is a great example of the research design not taking into account <a href="https://sylvan.fish/2023/02/09/experiments-equilibrium-13.html">equilibrium effects</a>.</p>

<p>For years the existence of the ranking algorithm has influenced both the types of content produced both by content creators and by the social media company itself. Turning off the ranking algorithm for a small subset of users for just a couple weeks is <em>not</em> a good hint at what the world would look like in the absence of a ranking algorithm.</p>

<p>If you have a ranking algorithm, there’s no penalty for just firehosing tons of content into the ether, relying on the algorithm to pick out the cream of the crop to bring to the top. If you turn off the algorithm, everyone will hate you because they are suddenly inundated with terrible content. But in a world that never had an algorithm in the first place, it’s unlikely that so much mediocre content would exist in the first place.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="causality" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Back in the day when I used to work at a particular social media company I saw an internal report describing how ranking, or the process of changing the order of content in user feeds, was provably a good thing. This was in the face of both public pressure from scholars and commentators describing how content ranking algorithms created bias and opportunities for controversial, divisive content to go viral and other kinds of bad things.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Randomized Experiments Can’t Always Detect Equilibrium Effects</title><link href="/2023/02/09/experiments-equilibrium-13.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Randomized Experiments Can’t Always Detect Equilibrium Effects" /><published>2023-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-02-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2023/02/09/experiments-equilibrium-13</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/02/09/experiments-equilibrium-13.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="1-rcts-causal-inference-and-internal-and-external-validity">1. RCTs, Causal Inference, and Internal and External Validity</h1>

<h2 id="you-can-skip-this-section-if-you-know-any-of-the-above-words">(you can skip this section if you know any of the above words)</h2>

<p>RCT (randomized controlled trials) are considered the gold standard in social science for determining causal effects - that is whether some intervention or treatment caused a change or outcome Y. The idea is pretty basic. You randomly split your participants into two groups, give one of them treatment, measure outcomes and argue that the average difference<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> between the groups represents a causal effect, since there’s absolutely no reason to expect that the groups are different from each other in any meaningful way (because they were assigned randomly).</p>

<p>Tech companies have taken this idea and run with it. Facebook is famous for running thousands of experiments on its users simultaneously all the time. Maybe 1% of users are seeing more posts from friends in their news feed compared to everyone else. After two weeks, the team running the experiment will look at some metrics like time spent scrolling News Feed, or number of likes or comments written. If people who see more posts from friends spend more time on Facebook, they’ll roll out the change to everyone. This is roughly how Facebook, and many other companies, “optimize” their product: someone dreams up a change, engineers build it, it gets tested for a bit, and then if the metrics look good it gets shipped.</p>

<p>Curiously, in the social sciences many academics would say that a “single experiment is not enough to determine policy,” which is precisely what tech companies use RCTs for (and increasingly NGOs and governments when evaluating policy programs!<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>). The concerns from academics usually boil down to something called “external vs internal validity.” Internal validity refers to the idea that the effect of the treatment is accurately estimated <em>for the people in your experiment.</em> Most RCTs have near-perfect internal validity. External validity, on the other hand, refers to the idea that the <em>results of the experiment generalize to a larger population</em>.</p>

<p>There are a bunch of reasons why external validity might be dubious in an RCT. For example, if you only did your experiment on young women, one might be suspicious that the effects generalize to older men. In this post, I want to focus on a specific kind of external validity violation, which is actually a risk for many experiments.</p>

<h1 id="2-equilibrium-effects">2. Equilibrium Effects</h1>

<h2 id="a-risk-for-interpreting-the-results-of-any-experiment-to-inform-policy">a risk for interpreting the results of any experiment to inform policy</h2>

<p>The Heisenberg effect (which roughly says that one cannot know both the position and momentum of a particle at a given time) is popularly confused with the observer effect, which says that the act of measuring [the position or momentum of a particle] will actually mess with the position or momentum of that particle, since there’s no way to measure something without actually interacting with it.</p>

<p>In a similar way, it’s often impossible to know the equilibrium effect of rolling out a treatment to a large audience based on a randomized experiment involving a smaller sub-audience. This is because for most people in the actual world, the status quo hasn’t changed, even if it’s different for people participating in the experiment.</p>

<p>Call your treatment Z. By construction, everyone in your experiment lives in a world where not-Z is the norm. Your experiment randomly gives Z for half the actors in your experiment. But importantly, you can only measure the effect of “having Z when most people have not-Z.” This is a different effect of “having Z when everyone else also has Z,” which would be the case if you were to “roll out” the policy globally.<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p>In medicine, this kind of effect doesn’t really matter. Someone’s reaction to a specific type of surgery doesn’t really change if a bunch of other people suddenly get access to that same type of surgery. But in social science, where we study behavior of people, this kind of effect <em>can matter a lot</em><sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>. This is because people in the world react to policy changes around them.</p>

<p>Maybe an experiment shows that increasing the amount of video in News Feed improves time spent on Facebook. Let’s say that it’s because most of the videos posted to Facebook are actually pretty good and interesting videos, and people like good, interesting content. You roll out the change to 100% of users. Media companies and influencers realize that if they post a video, it’s going to get boosted in feed. Suddenly, tons of content is being produced in video form. A lot of it is actually kind of terrible - it would be better as a news article or a photo. User welfare is actually worse than before, and people start using Facebook less because they’re sick of all the crappy video content.</p>

<p>One way to think about it is that by rolling out the change, you change the “game” (in the game theoretic sense) of the environment, and that the natural equilibrium actions of the actors within your environment will also change. When you run a randomized experiment, it’s really hard to structure it such that the “policy environment” equilibirum shifts at the same time, because by definition you’re not actually changing the policy environment for everyone.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Technical note: other estimators for the causal effect exist but for clarity and simplicity I’ll only discuss difference-in-means here <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Citation needed. Maybe a good topic for a follow-up post! <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Careful readers will note that the Heisenberg effect is not really the most commesurate analogy. I am open to suggestions for other names. “Policy Environment Equilibrium Effect” doesn’t really have the same ring to it. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>Antibiotic performance is a pretty good counter-example from medicine. The experiment tells you that antibiotics are great, when the status quo is not-very-much antibiotics. But if everyone gets antibiotics, then we breed super-bacteria that are resistant to antibiotics. This result is completely unpredicted by the randomized experiment. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing" /><category term="causality" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Internal vs. external validity round 1]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Doing things you want</title><link href="/2023/02/07/do-what-you-want-12.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Doing things you want" /><published>2023-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-02-07T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2023/02/07/do-what-you-want-12</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/02/07/do-what-you-want-12.html"><![CDATA[<p>A friend came to me with a problem. They wanted to make a big life decision X. But, they were worried that in 40 years, they would look back at what became of their life, disappointed with things, because they could see a story that started with making decision X and continued by making lots of decisions of type X, and finally after making forty years of decisions of type X feeling like they had wasted their life.</p>

<p>This happens to me a lot. X is usually low risk (in a traditional sense), secure, maybe externally prestigious, socially legible, but not necessarily aligned with what that friend actually wants to spend their time doing. Committing to long term relationships, staying in dissatisfying but well paying jobs, taking prestigious PhD program offers in departments that don’t actually fit their interests, and so on.</p>

<p>It’s a hard situation to find yourself in, because there isn’t a reliable global heuristic<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. Follow your whimsy, and you end up like Diogenes: masturbating in a barrel in the public square. Don’t, and wake up one day wondering why you never did anything you actually wanted to do and suffer under the crushing realization that you never will.</p>

<p>I think the slippery-slope worst-case outcome - that you’ll continue to make decision X because you’re making it now - deserves more deconstruction. The claim is two-fold; first, that you make decision X now, and second that <em>you continue to make it forever into the future</em>. This second component is doing a lot of heavy lifting in creating this worst-case outcome anxiety.</p>

<p>It’s OK to make decision X, just as it is to make decision not-X. The only thing that makes it not OK is making infinity of decision X (or not-X). Don’t do that.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>For grad students, tech workers, and general overachievers, I would actually say that you’ve probably been so overconditioned to ignore internal will in favor of external sources of validation that almost always the correct play is to take the high risk choice toward actualization. But not everyone comes from that world. Maybe another time I’ll write more about this. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A friend came to me with a problem. They wanted to make a big life decision X. But, they were worried that in 40 years, they would look back at what became of their life, disappointed with things, because they could see a story that started with making decision X and continued by making lots of decisions of type X, and finally after making forty years of decisions of type X feeling like they had wasted their life.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Capitalism-ization of Diversity</title><link href="/2023/02/06/diversity-11.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Capitalism-ization of Diversity" /><published>2023-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-02-06T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2023/02/06/diversity-11</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/02/06/diversity-11.html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently in the L-train subway a new set of subway ads have gone up marketing a Muslim-specific dating app.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.globaldatinginsights.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/Screen-Shot-2021-11-18-at-11.49.48.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>I guess this is sort of a good thing, in the sense that Muslims in New York deserve as much as others to participate in the quagmire-hellhole that is online dating. Anything less would smack of inequality of opportunity! But online-dating-culture gripes aside, this feels like it’s part of a growing trend that I’ll ungracefully call “the capitalism-ization of diversity.”</p>

<p>Broadly, it seems like the market has figured out that it can extract value from relatively untapped markets by targeting minority groups with culturally specific marketing and product. Big banks change their logos for Pride or Black History Month, Marvel movies like Shang-Chi and Black Panther get made, and dating apps expand their market to Muslims and Mormons.</p>

<p>Back in the early days of television and mass media all the commentators were worried about mass media causing the <em>homogenization</em> of society. The idea was that it would be easier for advertisers and corporations to sell to a larger group of more similar consumers. Since advertisers and corporations controlled the media, we would naturally see a shift toward social and cultural homogenization. Given this, the capitalism-ization of diversity seems surprising, since we’re seeing what looks like a celebration and highlighting of social and cultural diversity instead. Mass media culture largely ignored alternative culture; certainly, you would never see a subway ad in the early 2000s (well, for a lot of different reasons) that <em>opened</em> with “Halal! Inshallah!”</p>

<p>But another view is that it’s really all just homogenization under the hood; a way to capture and bend even more people to a dominant meta-culture where one expresses themselves primarily through media and product consumption. I think this inherent hypocrisy/subterfuge is what makes this trend so strangely discomforting. There’s no real celebration of counter-culture<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>, merely a perverse reflection of neoliberalist hegemony into different skin tones.</p>

<p>Congratulations, now <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">insert marginalized community here</code> gets to writhe under the thumb of late stage capitalism and desperately consume to fill the void in their souls just as much as everyone else.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1" role="doc-endnote">
      <p>I am using cultural/racial diversity, counter-culture, and alternative culture to all reference the same thing in this short piece. They technically refer to pretty different things, but I think one of the most important features of diversity and the whole point of “respecting” or learning about other cultures is that they offer meaningfully different <em>ways of life</em> from each other. The capitalism-ization of diversity threatens to erase those differences and reduce them to surface level traits. <em>DAE muslim??? Halal!!!</em> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Recently in the L-train subway a new set of subway ads have gone up marketing a Muslim-specific dating app.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Delay</title><link href="/2023/02/04/timedelays-10.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Delay" /><published>2023-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-02-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2023/02/04/timedelays-10</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/02/04/timedelays-10.html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://nuum.co/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/opening-doctored.png" alt="" /></p>

<p>The performer and her <a href="https://nuum.co/project/doppelganger">doppelganger</a> stand still for a moment. She turns her head to the left. Her doppelganger follows suit. The doppelganger is the performer, but five seconds in the past.</p>

<p>It’s cold today. Wind howls through the street. The farmer’s market is closed.</p>

<p>A tech company starts sending more irrelevant notifications from its app to a random subset of its users. After a couple weeks, those users spend more time using the app compared to the others. The tech company rolls out the change to all of its users. A year later, I uninstall the app because the notifications are too annoying.</p>

<p>The farmer’s market is closed today because twenty years ago there were too many chloroflourocarbons in the atmosphere.</p>

<p>The doppelganger is the performer, but five minutes in the past. The performer turns her head to the right. The doppelganger is sitting in a chair, tying her shoes. Five minutes later, the doppelganger turns her head to the right. But I’ve already forgotten.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hot and Cold Media: Google Maps Edition</title><link href="/2023/02/03/maps-9.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hot and Cold Media: Google Maps Edition" /><published>2023-02-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-02-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2023/02/03/maps-9</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/02/03/maps-9.html"><![CDATA[<p>When you’re using Google Maps navigation, the default perspective is first-person. The map is rotated and scaled to match your perspective as the driver/walker/biker: up is forward, down is backward, left and right both correspond to the real world left and right, assuming you’re holding your phone in its typical orientation. If you make a turn, the whole map rotates with you to maintain the correct first-person perspective.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/support-forums-api/attachment/thread-14375376-1383617846373138535.png" width="256px" /></p>

<p><em>The default Google Maps perspective</em></p>

<p>It’s really easy to see why this might be a good idea. Paper maps are normally oriented north-south, but most of the time when I’m trying to get from point A to point B I don’t care about whether I’m about to turn to the west - I just want to know if I need to go right or left. Paper maps don’t turn automatically, but I used to sometimes physically rotate maps to match the perspective I was seeing, a low-tech way of doing what Google maps navigation does automatically.</p>

<p>Marshall Mcluhan might describe this as a “hot” map media experience. The media is “high definition,” a simulation of reality rather than a mere representation. Paper maps are most certainly “cold,” requiring its users to do a fair bit of mental work to translate what they’re seeing on the map to the physical, geospatial reality around them.</p>

<p>I don’t miss having to page through an atlas to plan a road trip but I do think that there’s something that is lost when first person Google maps style navigation becomes the primary way used to navigate through place. I notice that I can almost never remember basic directions to routes I’ve driven dozens of times, and even if I might know that place A is 5 minutes away from place B and place C is 10 minutes away from place B, I have no idea where place A might be relative to place C. Google maps enables a kind of shitty teleportation, where I don’t have to pay any attention to my surroundings as I navigate them - I merely follow directions and get to where I’m going, thanks to how “hot” the map technology is (in Mcluhan’s sense of the word).</p>

<p>It’s this kind of thing that makes stories of people following Google/Apple maps into a desert to the point of being stranded seem actually believable.</p>

<p>You can force north-south orientation even during navigation by tapping the compass icon (at least at the time of this writing). This one weird trick™ already helps to recover some of the “coolness” of a paper map (pun intended). I notice very quickly if I’ve accidentally routed to the wrong place, since I have a vague sense of whether my destination is north/south/east/west of my current location. I can improvise shortcuts and detours around random construction or school buses. I have a sense of where different things are relative to each other, since I’m forced to constantly evaluate relative positions and directions as I navigate.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/support-forums-api/attachment/thread-2851431-14251814094790275470.png" width="256px" /></p>

<p><em>The north-south orientation navigation view</em></p>

<p>Here’s to hoping that Google never kills this feature. “Cold” tech is a rare thing.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When you’re using Google Maps navigation, the default perspective is first-person. The map is rotated and scaled to match your perspective as the driver/walker/biker: up is forward, down is backward, left and right both correspond to the real world left and right, assuming you’re holding your phone in its typical orientation. If you make a turn, the whole map rotates with you to maintain the correct first-person perspective.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Validate your shit</title><link href="/2023/02/02/validation-8.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Validate your shit" /><published>2023-02-02T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-02-02T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2023/02/02/validation-8</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/02/02/validation-8.html"><![CDATA[<p>when reading paper or at talk with fancy scary machine learning or text analysis technique.</p>

<p>think what is dumbest way. ask if fancy way really better.</p>

<p>how understand differences in language usage? count how many word different no use embeddings or topic model.</p>

<p>try predict which campaign ad persuasive with machine learning? guess probably no effect every time probably better.</p>

<p>want know which tweet about politics? see if has word “democrats” or “republicans” in it. no build BERT transformer classifier.</p>

<p>sometimes fancy way look good but only from certain angle like <a href="https://grugbrain.dev/">grug</a> in mirror.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[fancy don't make good]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How many calves go into whey?</title><link href="/2023/02/01/whey-7.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How many calves go into whey?" /><published>2023-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2023/02/01/whey-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/02/01/whey-7.html"><![CDATA[<p>You could say I’m ve-curious.</p>

<p>Question: how many calves need to be born in order to produce 1kg of whey protein powder?</p>

<p>Answer: about 0.07! One pregnancy lasts for a year with the cow producing 8 gallons or 30L per day. That’s about 11KL per calf. Meanwhile, it takes 200L of milk to yield 1kg of whey protein, so each pregnancy yields about 15kg of whey protein (and about 25x as much casein).</p>

<p>Apparently dairy cows also only give birth three times generally before being slaughtered for beef.</p>

<p>This exercise is a little cold and morbid but I genuinely was curious what the environmental and (potential) moral cost of dairy/whey consumption was. In general it’s a lot lower than I expected, although I haven’t done THAT much work to double check the figures. It’s kind of insane that a dairy cow produces 11KL of milk over the course of a year during one pregnancy. That’s just an absurd quantity.</p>

<p>From a cow life experience point of view, probably not awesome being milked 24/7 for three years in a row and then slaughtered.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[You could say I’m ve-curious.]]></summary></entry></feed>